Starr, T. mss., 1904-1997 LMC 2647
Lilly Library
Starr, T. mss.
1904-1997
Lilly Library
Starr, Tramp (Carl Wilson), 1885-1946
LMC 2647
3 Boxes 3 standard
The Starr, T. mss., 1904-1997, consist of the correspondence and papers of poet Carl Wilson, known as Tramp Starr.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift: 2005
Biographical Note
Carl Wilson, a.k.a. Tramp Starr, was born in Clark's Hill, Indiana in 1885, the son of a Methodist minister. He lived much of his life in Moores Hill, Indiana, but did venture west in his youth to try his hand at horsemanship and become a cowhand. Upon returning to Indiana, he met and married 15 year-old Marjorie Mitchell of Worthington.
Wilson began writing under the name "Tramp Starr" and started publishing poems in the mid- to late-1920s, extolling the virtues of farming and rural living in Indiana. He was occasionally featured in The Indianapolis Star and was a regular contributor to Farm Life magazine, published in Spencer, Indiana. His column, called variously "Chimes and Chuckles from Curly Shingles" or "Jokes and Jingles from Curly Shingles" after his farm, was very popular with readers who appreciated his embrace of the joys of farming, the outdoors, and traditional homespun values.
In 1930, Wilson began reading his poems on the R.F.D. Radio Hour, which was broadcast on station WLW out of Cincinnati, Ohio. Listener response was exceedingly positive and Wilson received fan letters from as far away as West Virginia and Montana. However, in early 1931, Wilson and his poems were taken out of the format of the show. Wilson did continue to write and publish his poems after this point. In addition to his first book, My Indiana Farm, published around 1930, Wilson went on to write and publish Radio Rhymes (1933) and Pop. 359 (1941). He continued his contributions to The Indianapolis Star and various other periodicals and also earned money by speaking publicly around the state at conferences and meetings.
Wilson and his wife moved to Nashville, Indiana, in scenic Brown County, around 1944 and ran an inn. He continued to write and publish until June of 1946, when he died of a sudden heart attack at the age of 60. At the time of his death, Wilson was survived by his wife, four daughters, a son, and several grandchildren.
Often called "The Hoosier Poet," Wilson rejected this title whenever he could, as he felt this honor should be reserved for his forerunner and successful poet, James Whitcomb Riley. Despite his humility concerning his reputation, Wilson was proud of his contribution to the Hoosier state and the fact that every poem he had ever written had been published.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, poem manuscripts, clippings, scrapbooks, and other materials related to Tramp Starr's poetry and readings.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by material type.
American Literature--Indiana
- Correspondence
  - Letters, 1920s
    - Letters, 1922-1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters, January - August, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters, October - December, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1930
    - Letters, January - August, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Letters, September, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters, October 1-15, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letters, October 16-21, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letters, October 22-31, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letters, November 1-5, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters, November 6-9, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letters, November 10, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letters, November 11-15, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letters, November 16-20, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Letters, November 21-23, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Letters, November 24-30, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Letters, December 1-19, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letters, December 20-31, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letters, 1931
    - Letters, January, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Letters, Feburary - June, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Letters, July - December, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letters, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letters, January-April, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Letters, May, 1934 - December, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letters, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letters, 1937
    - Letters, January - April, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Letters, May - December, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Letters, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Letters, 1945-1958 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Letters, (undated) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Empty Envelopes [Received], 1928-1938 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Poem Manuscripts, (undated) (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous Items, 1930-1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Clippings / Magazines
  - Clippings, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1930-1944 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 1952-1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, 1973-03-14-1973-05-09 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, 1973-05-16-1973-05-23 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, 1973-05-30-1973-06-20 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, 1973-08-15-1974-03-13 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - News Clippings, 1974
    - Clippings, 1974-03-20-1974-04-10 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Clippings, 1974-04-17-1974-04-24 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Clippings, May 22, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Clippings, 1974-05-29-1974-06-05 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Clippings, 1974-06-19-1974-06-26 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Clippings, 1974-07-03-1974-07-10 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Clippings, 1974-07-17-1974-07-24 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Clippings, 1974-07-31-1974-08-07 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Clippings, 1974-08-28-1974-09-04 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Clippings, September 11, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Clippings, 1974-09-18-1974-11-06 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Clippings, 1997-07-09-1997-07-19 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Small clippings collage, 1940-1946 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Clippings, (undated) (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Scrapbooks
  - Scrapbook, 1924-1925 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1925-1930 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1930-1934 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1938-1939-05 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1938-1944 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook, 1939-05-1940-05 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook, 1940-05-1941-04 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook, 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 11)